Alright, good morning guys. That's what I like to hear. If that worship set didn't prepare you for this, I'm with Liz there. You might want to open up some ears. That was good stuff.
For you guys that don't know me, my name is Corey Smith. I had the privilege of being one of the elders here at Canvas Church.
You're either here today, we've got a packed house. If you're here today, you're either extremely lucky or Ryan made an announcement like two weeks ago that I was preaching and you forgot to mark your calendars.
It's a whole thing. So, if you're new here, I'm not the normal guy up here, but you will hear different voices from time to time.
And that's the way we like to have that structured. And, I'll get the mic this week. It's going to be like super awkward as you walk out now.
It's going to be a whole thing. So, just hang on. We won't be lost.
It seems like every time I get the opportunity to speak, and you guys have probably noticed a trend.
It's like, Corey Stockton, we're probably going to be somewhere in the Old Testament.
And there's some truth to that.
Not because I want to live under the Old Testament, but that I believe it adds so much more color and depth to the New Testament.
I love the idea that people set out to read their Bibles cover to cover in a year.
I love that goal. We're not quite to New Year's resolution, but that's a big thing in New Year's.
And I think that's an admirable goal.
But let me hit you with something that doesn't seem as easily achievable, and it's a long-term goal.
It's the idea of understanding context, history, and the Old Testament to add another layer of understanding to the writers of the New,
and to also round out an understanding of the greatest redemption story that the world has ever known.
Jim, I'm not discouraging you from reading your Bible cover to cover in a year.
If you heard that, or have a lot of ideas.
Like, if you heard something, erase it, and I'll try to unpack that.
But if you heard that, it's not what I'm trying to drive home here, but the idea that there is so much information in this book
that I'd rather you just understand a chapter of it than I would read the whole thing and not get anything out of it.
And I'll call myself out here, too.
I'm a big, we were talking out in the lobby, I'm a big, like, history nerd.
So, I love the knowledge of it, the head knowledge of it.
And it's an easy trap to get into this book and go, I have a ton of head knowledge, right?
But what we're seeking here, we're promised that there's application in this book that brings life and a life more abundant, we're promised.
See, a heart change, a heart that learns to speak after God constantly.
If he can do that for my heart, I know he can do that for yours.
So, that exists within this book.
There's application here.
So, today, I'm going to do my best, and we're going to try to tie the Old Testament and New together the way they were supposed to work in unison.
I've got a, like, half-running nose, so if y'all see me, like, I'd rather do that than sniffle in the mic, and Donovan would be, he'd be very mad if I sniffled in the mic all day.
So, I had the, when the writers of the New Testament referenced the Scriptures,
if we ever put context to this thought, that when the writers of the New Testament, they wouldn't have had the Bible as we know it.
So, when they referenced the Scriptures, they would have been referencing the Old Testament, the Torah, the prophets, the books of wisdom and history.
This was their Bible when Jesus walked with us and started his ministry.
So, Liz read an excerpt of Matthew 22 for us this morning, and the paragraph title for that probably reads,
and hers did, because we picked the translation, but the most important commandment.
And where did the most important commandment come from, right?
You heard the expert in religious law.
Who did it come from?
Moses.
So, it came from Moses.
And we're going to, that's what we're going to spend some time on today.
The most important commandment from the Scriptures, their Bible, and Jesus' reorientation of that,
in light of his divine presence and kingship come to earth, right?
What is, God, Jesus does this a lot with us, that we have a commandment,
but now, in light of his presence, his incarnation on earth, let me give you the heart of this, right?
Weaving the new and old together.
Today, we're going to be opening our Bibles, or your apps, to Deuteronomy 6.
That's real Old Testament.
And we're going to be covering verses 1 through 13, but I want you to pay special attention to verses 4 through 7,
and that's kind of where the meat of our text lies today.
And I'm going to, while Dave gets that up on the board, I'm going to try to set the stage for you real quick, right?
History, context, love that stuff, super nerd.
So, Deuteronomy is the fifth and last book of the Torah, the five books of Moses.
They're often called the Pentateuch, or the five books.
The Pentateuch, we got that.
So, we've gone from the creation account in Genesis, through the patriarchs, Abraham, Isaac, Jacob, to Joseph in Egypt.
And at the end of Genesis comes one of my favorite verses.
You meant evil against me, but God meant it for good.
And that's Genesis 50.
Joseph sets the stage for a God who responds and acts according to his own will, his own goodness, and not the evil that perpetrates our hearts.
See, then next we'll get into the book of Exodus, where Moses is caught up by God to free his people from captivity.
But that freedom wasn't without the wilderness and the hardships that go along with that.
See, now we're here where the book of Deuteronomy starts, and it's actually the same spot as the book of Numbers ends.
See, we're with the Israelites in Moab, on the doorstep of the Promised Land.
If you, I love doing this in my Bible studies and stuff, if you flip to the back of your Bible, this is the one thing the app does not have.
It's like, in the back of your Bible, there's these maps, and you're like, I don't mean anything to me.
But, if you get into there in an early map, you'll see kind of how the demons broken up in the land of Moab that sets there to the east of the Promised Land.
And then right across, what separates Moab from the Promised Land is the Jordan River and the Dead Sea.
Huge landmarks, if you've heard anything about Israel.
So, we're here with the Israelites in Moab, on the doorstep of the Promised Land.
See, of the five books of Moses, only three account for history.
Or the narrative of the identity of the nation of Israel, right?
These books are given an identity to a people.
The other two, Leviticus and Deuteronomy, speak of the law and of the covenant.
And as a people who are holy, are set apart by God.
Ezekiel 34, 31 says,
You are my flock, the sheep of my pasture.
You are my people, and I am your God.
The book of Deuteronomy literally means repetition of the law.
I say this from time to time.
Your Bible doesn't have a volume control.
So, if there's something to listen to, it's often repeated.
This book consists of three sermons or speeches, and the book of Deuteronomy consists of three sermons or speeches delivered to the Israelites by Moses,
who was not permitted to enter the Promised Land.
But who would have to pass that mantle on to another leader, Joshua.
These are his farewell addresses to the people he has led.
They recount 40 years in the wilderness, wandering, which have led them from the lands of Egypt and Pharaoh, death and slavery to the tabernacle and the Spirit of God residing among them.
To the fulfillment of the promise God made to Abraham and the patriarchs, we're here at the doorstep of the Promised Land.
God is faithful, and he will keep his covenants.
Second, I can picture the Israelites standing there in the land of Moab on the east side of the Jordan River in the Dead Sea.
They can smell the salt air.
They can see the vineyards and the houses.
They can almost taste the promises.
Their promised land lies right over there.
And what Moses finds most important, and this is what I find cool,
what Moses finds most important to tell them at this moment is to have them remember to observe the law and to follow God.
That they are a people, a holy people set apart.
One of my favorite titles for Yahweh is the Ancient of Days.
That's a cool title, huh?
Like, the Ancient of Days.
I mean, this rounds out.
If you notice, like, all God's titles just round out to be the best, which is super cool.
But you are my people, hand-picked by the Ancient of Days, the Lord of Lords, and the King of Kings.
So let's get into this.
Deuteronomy 6, 1 through 13.
And we got it up on the screen if you need it.
These are the commands, decrees, and regulations that the Lord your God commanded me to teach you.
You must obey them in the land you are about to enter and occupy.
And you and your children and grandchildren must fear the Lord your God as long as you live.
If you obey all his decrees and demands, you will enjoy a long life.
Listen closely, Israel, and be careful to obey.
Then all will go well with you, and you will have many children in the land flowing with milk and honey,
just as the Lord, the God of your ancestors, promised you.
Listen, O Israel, the Lord is our God, the Lord alone.
And you must love the Lord your God with all of your heart, all of your soul, and all of your strength.
And you must commit yourselves wholeheartedly to these commands that I am giving you today.
Repeat them again and again to your children.
Talk about them when you're at home, when you're on the road.
And I lost my spot.
And when you are going to bed and when you're getting up, tie them to your hands and wear them on your foreheads as reminders.
Write them on the doorposts of your house and on your gates.
The Lord your God will soon bring you into the land he swore to give you when he made a vow to your ancestors, Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob.
It is a land with large, prosperous cities that you did not build.
The houses will be richly stocked with goods that you did not produce.
You will draw water from cisterns that you did not dig.
And you will eat from vineyards and olive trees that you did not plant.
When you have eaten your fill in this land, be careful not to forget the Lord who rescued you from slavery in the land of Egypt.
You must fear the Lord your God and serve him.
When you take an oath, you must use only his name.
So it nails home an idea there, right?
And we won't talk about it as much, but the idea from verses 10 to 13, the idea that you will see these things that you had no investment in,
and you will reap the benefits of that.
God makes that promise in one condition, that they are faithful to him.
But where I primarily feel called to teach on today are verses 4 and 5.
And I'm even going to try, this Frederick County boy is even going to try to teach you a Hebrew word.
Are there any Hebrew scholars in the house before I do this?
No?
Because I'm probably going to butcher this.
So Dave, can you throw that Hebrew word up on the screen for me?
Shema.
Has anybody heard of this word before?
Good, good, good, good, good.
So if you Google the word Shema, you'll find that it's connected to a prayer that observing Jews would pray daily.
That they would pray verses 4 and 5.
And in that way, they would show obedience to the commands in verses 6 through 9, right?
They would teach their children.
They would do these things.
It's also been put to song, and it's a pretty powerful song.
And after today, I hope you, like, if you have Spotify, look it up.
But you can actually find, like, Shema songs that are pretty cool.
I don't speak a ton of Hebrew, so when I say a ton of Hebrew, I don't mean any.
But it's super cool to listen to it.
Shema would be the Hebrew word here in the beginning of verse 4.
The translators oftentimes use Shema as listen.
But like most ancient words, it packs far more of a punch than just listen.
In verse 4, it says, Shema, O Israel, the Lord is our God, the Lord alone.
See, I just talked about us missing what really encapsulates Shema in our English language.
When we think of listen, we think of just hearing, right?
Merriam-Webster just kind of affirms this idea.
And they define listening this way to pay attention to sound.
But even in our English, we subconsciously have a deeper meaning to the word listen, don't we?
How many people in this room are parents?
Oh, yeah.
How many?
I know at least one.
But how many people's parents in this room use them as a sermon illustration?
All right.
So my kids, they're going to be able to play that card.
If I ask my sons, why didn't you listen to me?
What am I implying?
They messed up.
They're not.
Are you hearing my words because your actions don't reflect that?
I'm implying that they didn't take action.
They didn't respond to the words that I gave them.
See, if I ask them to calm down or to clean their room or to stop throwing haymakers on each other,
I'll ask, why aren't you listening?
I can't say what I really say because we're in church.
They're like, for the benefit of today, it's why aren't you listening?
So the question, the question I'm asking doesn't mean their ears aren't receiving sound waves that my throat and lungs are creating.
The question means, we're ready for that next slide, Dave.
Why don't your reactions to my words, to a commandment, change what you are doing?
Shema, listening and responding.
See, I broke the shema in these two categories that will really help us take heart in what Moses is trying to portray to the people of Israel.
That God wants them to hear, but also respond to that hearing.
Next slide, Dave.
I'm going to give you some slides, but the Apostle James echoes this sentiment in James 1.22.
Don't just listen to God's word.
You must do what it says, otherwise you are only fooling yourselves.
Shema, listening and responding.
See, that's what makes that word so powerful.
It's a word that encapsulates not only the actions, but the reaction to the actions.
Listening and listening are the same verb in Hebrew.
Shema.
Next slide for Psalms 34.
God, I prayed to the Lord and he answered me.
He freed me from all my fears.
Those who look to him for help will be radiant with joy.
No shadow or shame will darken their faces.
In my desperation, I prayed and the Lord listened.
How do we know he listened?
Because he acted.
He saved me from all my troubles.
See, hearing requires a response.
So how do we, how do we feel we know God is answering our prayers?
Because we feel, and I'll answer to the room here, because we feel when he answers, he has heard us.
But why should we Christians expect that he would treat us any differently?
See, why do we, next slide, Dave, why do we expect God to move on our behalf if we're unwilling to move on his?
See, when God asks us to listen, Janvus, he expects a response to follow it.
See, listening without action is not listening.
The old saying comes to mind is, if a tree falls in the woods and no one is around it here, it doesn't make a sound.
If God asks us to listen and we don't respond, did we hear him?
Did you hear a cry in the woods for help but didn't investigate?
Or let's be honest, call 911 because there's a lot of true crime podcasts out there.
If you heard a cry for help and you didn't investigate or intervene on some level, did you listen to that cry?
See, we're diving into a motif here that is weaved throughout the Torah, into the books of history, and into the prophets, and on into the New Testament.
That listening and not listening to God becomes a theme.
Anyone who has ears, let him hear, let him shema.
Liz did a great job.
We coordinated the verses, but her prayer not told the sermon today.
He who has ears, let him hear.
Hopefully, a lot of these verses will mean new context for you now as you read through your Bible.
Let him listen and respond to the command of God.
Shema.
Listening and responding.
So back to the text at hand.
Shema, O Israel, the Lord is our God, the Lord alone.
In verse 5, and you must love the Lord your God with all of your heart, all of your soul,
and all of your strength.
Next slide, please.
Are we listening?
Are we responding to loving the Lord our God with all of our heart, soul, and strength?
See, when I wrote this, it's funny, because I, oftentimes, self-righteousness is a real thing, right?
I don't know if any of us really get out of it.
We can contend with it.
We can fight it.
But it's not something you just, I think, are good with.
Some people might be.
Not me.
I'm not over that yet.
When I was writing this sermon, I had to fight the urge to, like, when I first wrote it up,
I said, are we loving the Lord our God with all of our heart, soul, and strength?
The idea that I'm going to make it this unobtainable moral superiority argument.
This self-righteousness that says, I love God more than this person or that person, so I'm good.
Right?
So, I try to frame my sermons in this manner, and I'm a thousand percent preaching to myself.
I was telling, sidetracked here a little bit, I was telling Samantha the other day, I love
the idea of people just getting, sitting down in their alone time with God and just putting
a sermon together, because you'd be shocked at how much information that God is trying to
relay to you that you're writing down.
Are you responding, or daily, to God's commands?
You.
Not your neighbor.
Not Sally next door.
Is Sally in here?
I saw Jim.
Sally's not in here.
I was going to use her.
Tell her.
Not Sally next door.
You.
Are you responding?
And speaking of your neighbors, that's kind of my transition to roll into what Liz read
for us and what Jesus said about our neighbors.
See, we're going to come back to what was read before worship, right?
We're going to try to tie the old and the new together.
Matthew 22, 36 through 40 says, Rabbi, that's to say, teacher, what is the most important
commandment in the law of Moses?
And Jesus answered, you must love the Lord your God with all of your heart, all of your
soul, and all of your mind.
Anybody see a difference there?
You'll notice that difference, and I'm glad you did.
Some might be saying, why would it change?
And remember, translation and context.
Jesus would have been speaking in Aramaic, and the earliest manuscripts of Matthew would
have been recorded in Greek.
Most scholars agree that the replacement of mind over strength would be so that the Greeks
would better understand the Jews' reverence to their God.
Greece was the birthplace of philosophy, right?
The Jews pushing back against those Hellenistic influence would have said, strength also rest
in the mind.
We'll make this a philosophical argument that you are to love the Lord your God with everything
you are.
Verse 38, this is the first and greatest commandment.
See, if I were to stop here, I don't think that Jesus would have raised the eyebrows of the
Pharisees, right?
He was just like, you know what?
Love the Lord your God with all your heart.
You know, you guys probably prayed it this morning.
That's the best one.
They would have been like, okay, we can agree with that.
So the Shema, we talked about this earlier, was a daily prayer that most of the Jewish people
knew by heart.
It's not just, it's something they just probably recited that morning.
And the priest would actually wear parts of the Shema, another history lesson for another
time.
Jesus actually lets them have that in the next chapter of Matthew for being fears only and
wearing this stuff but not responding to it.
What I think Jesus is doing here is asking the Pharisees if their actions show a response
to God or are they only using empty words.
So that's why when Jesus responds, he adds this, a second is equally important.
Anyone else love when Jesus responds to a lawyer and he's like, you know what?
I'm going to use legal language.
That way you're not going to trap me in this.
So a second is equally important.
The second part of the greatest commandment is to love your neighbors as yourself, which
comes from Leviticus flood, Leviticus 19, 18.
Do not seek revenge or bear a grudge against a fellow Israelite, but love your neighbor as
yourself.
I am the Lord.
So I think we've, I think we've unpacked the Shema, so we have a communal understanding of
that word a little bit better now.
So let's spend some time unpacking the second portion, which is Matthew 22.
So love your neighbor as yourself.
And I'm sure you, you've heard this, right?
If you spend any time in church, this is a, it's a popular sermon for good reason, but
it's so good because Jesus unpacks it himself, right?
He gives us a parable, a life lesson to look to in Luke 10, 25 through 29.
An expert in religious law asks, what should I do to inherit in the current life?
Hopefully it's not like the same expert walking around like playing stump Jesus, like he's got
a bet going with the Pharisees and he's like, man, I think I got him this time.
Hopefully it's somebody different that gets stumped every time and they're, I still have
a heart to learn.
So the cool part is Jesus gives him the same response to what is the greatest commandment.
What must I do to inherit eternal life?
It's the same answer as what God gives us.
Jesus gives us as the greatest commandment.
The man answers with the greatest commandment, right?
He says, I love the Lord your God with all of your heart, soul, and mind, and I love my
neighbor as myself.
Jesus says, right.
I love the NLT.
They even have like an estimation point.
Right.
Jesus tells him, right.
Do this and you will live.
The man retorts, right?
Everybody, all of us always want to argue with Jesus.
The man retorts and says, he's my neighbor.
This is the part of the story where Jesus tells the parable of the good Samaritan.
And for the sake of time, we won't get into that today, but I encourage you to read through
that if you've never done so.
I'm going to give you the close-knit version.
Were you that type of like student where you're like, I'm not going to read the book.
I'm going to read the close-knit version today.
I'm in big company though.
Everyone is your neighbor.
The person sitting beside you.
The person living next to you.
The person whom you've never met, but you've just run into.
These people are your neighbors.
Christ followers or not.
Next slide, please, Dave.
Not everyone is your brother or sister in Christ, but everyone is your neighbor.
See, Jesus is tapping into our humanity here.
He doesn't tell us to love our neighbor as our wife or as we love our parents or our children
as someone that's easy to love, right?
He doesn't tell us to love our neighbor if they have the same political ideology as us.
He doesn't tell us to love our neighbor as a Democrat or a Republican or how they deserve to be loved.
He doesn't tell us to love our neighbors if they look like us.
He tells us to love our neighbors as we love ourselves.
Let's make this really practical.
If you have enough, if you were hungry, would you eat?
Yeah.
If you were full, would you feed someone else?
If you were cold, would you warm yourself up?
If you were warm, would you help someone else get there?
If you had enough, would you make sure someone else did too?
Next slide.
If we, as followers of Jesus, lived out these two commands, the greatest commandment, we could change the world.
Jesus said the law and all the demands of the prophets are based on these two commandments.
I read earlier when I was doing some research for this that a first century Hebrew rabbi said that the entire Hebrew Bible huges on the Shema.
The rest of it is just context around it.
Think about that.
Listen, O Israel.
Shema, O Israel.
You must love the Lord your God with all of your heart, soul, and mind.
See, that's the hearing portion of the greatest commandment, right?
To, you must do this.
This is what you're hearing.
Love the Lord your God with all of your heart, soul, and mind.
What's the response to that?
To love your neighbor as yourself.
So when I was working through this sermon, a Tim Keller quote popped up.
That's a time I'll call for a document to come up.
That religion says, I obey, therefore I'm accepted.
And the gospel says, I'm accepted, therefore I obey.
So that's the difference, right, is Shema, hearing and responding.
If I hear a command from God, I'm going to respond to that command to let him know I'm receiving it.
See, we're about to the end of my message now.
We're going to do a time of communion together.
But before we do that, I pulled this rule perfectly in today.
If you've heard from the Holy Spirit today, convicting you of a response to something,
I encourage you to seek someone out to respond to that call.
Whether it's a response to finally submit your life to King Jesus,
or it's a response of a life out of sync with what God has told us.
See, if you need to talk to someone today, we're here.
We're going to make ourselves available for that, right?
Because that's part of our listening, our responding to being open to that.
I've asked Dave Bounder to hang out with me up here.
If you've got something you need to respond to, we're here for that.
Communion.
Hopefully you grabbed a cup on your way in.
It's just such an easy sermon for application because it's literally listening and doing,
which is easy in the play-by-play, right?
But in application, that becomes a little bit harder to do.
If you didn't grab a communion cup, you'll want to grab one on your way out.
But this, as followers of Jesus, is our response to his actions on the cross.
The remembrance of his body broken and his blood spilled,
as he showed us an example of true love, right?
Even more than loving someone as yourself,
but loving someone more than yourself.
His creation, his people, he loved more than himself.
So let us take this bread as a remembrance of Christ's body broken for us.
Give me a second because I didn't preempt it.
Ooh, this is a key one.
I'm wearing a white shirt, too,
which is probably, yeah.
We really hit the jackpot on these.
All right.
So together, as a body, as a family of Christ,
we're going to take the bread.
My bird's dry anyways.
This weaver really helped.
Really good.
And let's drink this juice as a remembrance of Christ's blood still for us.
But, church, let's also remember that this, we do this week in and week out,
and I hope we're not losing the significance of this.
But this is a picture of a meal, right?
We have the picture of the Last Supper, but this is a celebration.
We don't have real wine in here.
We have grape juice, but this is a real wine.
This will be a celebration, right?
An idea that we're breaking bread together, and we're celebrating the victory that one day we will be reunited with our Lord Christ Jesus.
See, we're the Israelites right now.
We're set free from slavery and death, but we're awaiting our promised kingdom, right?
We're in that wilderness.
We're in that in-between.
So let's pray.
Dear Heavenly Father, may we be a people who hear.
May we be a people who respond to your voice.
May I be a person who hears.
May I be a person who responds to your voice, Lord Jesus.
Make within us a fiery compassion.
Not to just have people hear you, but also see you within us, Lord.
May we be a people who bring about revival.
We shine our lights in the darkness of people who are not just hearers of the word, but doers as well.
Thank you, Jesus, for your sacrifice.
Thank you, Jesus, for your glory.
And your church.
To be the people who proclaim your lordship to the four corners of the earth.
May we act like we've heard that calling, Lord.
In Jesus' name we pray.
Amen.
Thanks, church.
May go in peace.
Hey, I'm only five minutes over.